hello everyone this is Frankie Freitas
and welcome to another week of holotalk
for the week of April 10th 2000. uh
we're bringing you a special show this
week we have been running a series of
shows that we recorded at the center for
the holographic arts in Long Island City
New York but we had some news come
through that we've been waiting for for
quite some time and I'd like to at least
dedicate this program to that news our
special guest this week is going to be
friends Ross from Ross Brooks and I'm
joined right now with Michelle Roy once
again in the studio Michelle how you
doing I'm good how are you okay because
you're involved with this project to
some extent as well to quite a bit
extent in some areas that we'll get into
in just a second but what's happened is
over the past year or maybe a little bit
more than a year we've been working with
Ross books who has published the
holography handbook and holography
Marketplace to publish shoebox
holography as a regular book as many of
you know that shoebox logography was
designed around the semiconductor lasers
and a little system that students are
using and even some amateurs and
hobbyists
Franz Ross gave me a call and said they
were interested in doing the book A
little over a year ago and since that
time we've been working on it and now
it's going to be released on April 14th
and will be available in bookstores
across the country and also your regular
internet Outlets such as amazon.com
Barnes and Nobles Etc Michelle's
involved with this to the point that you
did a appendix to the book as far as
Career Development with students and
along that vein what I'd like to do
having you on the show right now is to
get a few of your thoughts on how you
feel the shoebox holography ties into
the educational curriculum of a lot of
the schools
think that one of the trends that we see
in schools is that they're moving to
more project-oriented curricula where
kids are rather than sitting and reading
a book about lasers or holography or
whatever not that they don't need to
read books
um but actually having Hands-On
experiences particularly in The Sciences
is incredibly important in terms of
helping kids understand the underlying
you know scientific principles and how
everything works and I think that the
great thing about the shoebox book is
that it shows teachers and students you
know step by step how to go through a
project of creating a hologram that
gives kids a real hands-on experience
with the technology and the scientific
principles Plus for fact that a lot of
schools are going to more
interdisciplinary approaches where
they're having you know it's not just uh
you know one subject on its own and
there's so many you know math physics
you know all of those things tie into
what you do with shoebox so you know
that's a real opportunity for for
teachers to do something that's not only
project oriented and Hands-On but also
uh interdisciplinary yeah so who is the
shoebox logography guy that allowed
holography itself to become part of the
state standards in Florida with
communication Technologies and the way
that bill Pugh and I worked on that was
showing it was very important that we
showed how other areas of Education can
tie in right how it hit on different
standards and Most states are moving to
standards-based education so if schools
are looking for a way to you know have a
unit you know in a science class or
whatever that hits across multiple
standards because many schools are
complaining well how the heck are we
supposed to cover all of this you know
in a school earlier over the course of a
kid's life in the schools well this is
something that hits across multiple
standards and so those would you know be
satisfied in one project yeah um so and
by the end of this school year I will
have a program guide together for
teachers which will show them how they
can bring a number of different students
with different interests into this whole
process and all centered around the
Science and Technology of shoebox
photography well you could even have
teachers working together to on the you
know you could have the teachers that
have who have the same kids in the
science class you know and and they work
together so that it's actually the same
kids yeah just in their different
classes so we'll get that program to
guide together for teachers as well and
you would be able to order that along
with the shoebox holography book itself
also another area of the book that you
wrote yourself that careers careers
right careers yeah and you want to tell
the uh yeah yeah I mean very quickly one
of the things that we wanted to do was
um not was also look at how you know if
kids found that they were interested or
anyone found that they were interested
did in the whole field of laser
symphotonics as a result of going
through the shoebox halography they
could then explore different career
options so that the appendix that I
wrote basically talks about what are the
different aspects that you have to
consider in career development we did a
show you know earlier in the season
talking about that but then also has you
know specific links to explore careers
in lasers and photonics links to
education programs and so forth so
that's all in that appendix so that if
kids or whoever are interested in
getting into a career they could you
know do some more exploration and I
would like to thank you and Bill freed
and kind of the freelance group for
career and Workforce Innovation for
providing the materials to go into the
shoebox holography book which will
definitely be a great resource for
teachers and Educators and hobbyists if
they would they'd like to get more
information maybe even for a career
change somewhere down the line
all right we're going to move on to our
Interview With Friends Ross uh friends
is out in California is Ross books and
like I'd mentioned before they also
published the holography handbook which
has been the Bible of holography for
many many years and now they have
shoebox logophy and once again it's
going to be available through bookstores
across the country and also through your
internet outlets and also at the hollow
World site you can order it there we
will have uh ordering at the hollow
World site itself and it started off as
that little guide that I put up on the
web that I think was last March or
something like that and uh but it's
become look what it's become and
hopefully we can bring kids into this
field I'm getting emails about kids
winning first place science fair yeah
that competition I love the one that you
showed me last night oh yes yeah nice
yeah yeah she was so psyched and she got
a special award from women in
engineering okay this
you know young lady right may have a
future in photonics laser Communications
yeah it was filled with exclamation
points so that's how you know she was
excited very excited and we're very
excited yeah that was excellent don't
want to use the show as something as a
sales tool but as many of you know and
have been listening for the past three
years I rarely get on here to sell
anything but this is something that's
happening with holography and I just
happen to be involved with it so I have
to report on that as well so let's move
on to our interview with Franz Ross
thank you for tuning in and I hope
with myself and hopefully uh more visits
with Michelle Roy okay okay okay thanks
for tuning in bye
hello talk listeners this is for Freitas
and we have someone on the line here who
needs no introduction at all it's Franz
Ross from Ross books Publishing House of
holography marketplace and holography
handbook friends how are you
I'm doing great it's been a long road
hasn't it yeah it sure has uh you know
we've gone through a uh a lot of
addition to the holography marketplace
and we've got gone through a few uh you
know editions of the handbook and all
and uh every time we come out with
something we try to improve a little bit
you know now we're doing shoebox
holography right and that's very
interesting the way that came up
um you know we we pretty
handbook in the uh the handbook explains
to people how to go about building their
own little studio and creating their own
Holograms and a fairly inexpensive
amount of money but uh
that we have been getting over time is
that there still exists a a large number
of people particularly people that are
right at the very very beginning stage
or maybe in schools for example where
they have extremely limited budgets yeah
and
people have been coming back and saying
that they just they can't get the
authorization for the space or for the
amount of money that's needed to go out
and do a decent job of making a nice lab
you know nice programs and so we're very
excited about that and you know during
the course the development of the book
a high school teacher even called in as
I understand and became very excited
about it tried it out with the students
and uh golly you know I talked to the
guy personally and then like you know
lots of pictures of all the students
running around making Holograms and
they're very involved with it I mean
they enjoy it very much and it uh it
seems like it felt a need you know yeah
yeah I imagine the book will be
available in bookstores
yeah it should be available uh this
month actually April probably toward the
end of the month and um you know we're
really looking forward to it very happy
I know the book will be available online
at your site but will it also be
available to people like through
Amazon.com and things yeah as a matter
of fact we have a relationship with
amazon.com and uh what Amazon wants us
to do is as soon as we you know uh get
the first books off the press to send it
to them and they'll put it up there and
it'll be available in Amazon as well and
uh other places too you know
you know we have relationships with
Library Distributors and regular
Distributors it takes a while to get
into the pipeline yeah it's the type of
publication you might not find in every
single bookstore because you know I mean
it's not the kind of thing you make
movies out of you know
yeah I'm sure we could make a movie out
of this has it been over a year yeah as
a matter of fact it did it have taken
about a year hasn't it yeah but uh you
know I think it was time well spent you
know it's the kind of thing that uh you
want to go back and forth on and uh you
know in the development of the book you
know we tried a lot of different things
right yeah yeah
um
one of the things that uh took a little
extra time was uh adding the fiber optic
chapter yes
really nice we are contacted by John
clayer who's been on this show already
and John does Holograms inside of caves
and he had mentioned that he was working
on using the laser pointers to do fiber
optic Holograms so uh John worked with
us and helped us get a chapter together
and Steve Michael did a lot of the
experimentation with that confirming the
results and things as well another thing
that really excites me about it uh you
know is just that it seems like if
you're trying to introduce the children
to uh you know or beginning people
through holography there's nothing more
exciting than than seeing uh the light
from the laser run through a little
fiber optic too and then that fiber
optic tube be used to expose the the
whole
yeah you know it uh and it's it's very
interesting and very appealing and also
showing the kids that this technology is
used in everyday applications with
communication Technologies and that's
something that they could actually grow
up and move into that field as a career
someday right the really nice thing
about it is that uh the instructor or
someone that brings us into their school
and sets it up for
Pocket Change you know they are are able
to bring in a lot of other disciplines
you know they can bring in uh
fundamental Optics you know
they can discuss fiber optics and how
it's used in not only uh in making
Holograms here but also used in
Communications and so forth and you know
they're a lot of a lot of add-on uh
disciplines that they can give
fundamental lectures on in an
introduction to and have a very wide
group of students involved with it as
well a lot of a lot of different
applications there yeah yeah yeah there
are a lot of different applications that
you can find for it the really nice
thing about it is that because it's at
the uh at the beginning level you don't
have to be you know a physics student
that's uh you know you know well along
into the uh
instructional course in order to be able
to appreciate it and and play with it
it's more like a sort of a
introductory Physics course type of
experiments see the
nice thing about it the other feedback
that we got from schools is that when
you have something like making a
hologram in a class
are very interested in that because they
get to put their hands on the objects
they get to move them around they get to
make something yes and then when they're
done with it they can actually walk out
and go home with something they've got a
little show and tell item there and uh
what we've found is that uh in an awful
lot of the schools where this type of
course is uh is allowed to be put on the
curriculum they they have a very large
sign up you know a great deal of
interesting yeah and there's no doubt
that the educational sector is going to
be one of the biggest groups to benefit
by shoeboxography but another group also
would be artists who did not want to
initially make that large investment to
experiment with holography now they can
actually just get started on their own
at a very reasonable cost and see if
it's something that they want to move on
to that's exactly what I what I feel in
there the uh if it's done in a school
setting well of course they can have the
opportunity to discuss with other people
that are like-minded what they about it
and you know look at different resources
and so forth and think about whether you
know they want to move up to the next
level and buy a decent laser and what
kind of laser is a decent laser yeah and
for individuals that want to do it at uh
at home by themselves I mean the really
good thing about it is that you're able
to witness the phenomena you know and
see that it actually does work and uh
it's not a great cause to you the whole
thing can be done you know less than a
hundred dollars and um you know it um it
gives you a feeling for uh what's
involved in making a hologram so that
you know you can then if you want to
step up to the next level and build your
own little Studio or you know something
a little more advanced yeah it's sort of
going to do for holography with the
holography handbook did back when it was
released yeah I think that at the
introductory level uh you know a lot of
the people that were
um uh that would look at the handbook
and read through it and uh and say to
themselves I'm really interested but the
problem is I I can't quite justify to
myself the uh the space and the money
well those people will be captured I
mean they're well you know we'll still
be able to uh be introduced to the field
of pornography by doing uh you know the
shoebox allography experiment is it
spiral bound yeah
bound so that you know you can turn to
any individual page and have it just you
know lie flat so that you can use it as
a recipe book in fact uh I think that
you and Steve and to Great length to
make sure that uh the exposures and all
are you know reasonably accurate of
course everybody understands that uh
diode lasers which are very inexpensive
you know the laser pointers are not the
thing that they you know uh uh you know
a powerful CW laser are a very expensive
laser but they are capable of producing
the uh exposures and you know what what
this book does is it uh it gives you a
specific Emulsion and a specific
exposure and you know distances and
everything that you need so that you can
produce the product yes and without that
you know there would be an awful lot of
disappointment I think on the part of a
lot of people now you had mentioned to
me that April 14th some of the books
will be ready off of the press when
would someone be able to order this for
themselves well they can actually order
the book now since we're only one about
a week or so away here and uh any order
that is uh received you know will you
know be
one of the first order spelled so I mean
you should give the book within a couple
of weeks you know and we should ship
within a couple of weeks okay
well I guess it's a time for celebration
now that we're finally finished with
this project and it was a great
experience for me to be able to work on
a project like this and I want to thank
you very much for the opportunity to put
shoebox photography out there well I
just want to thank you an awful lot for
what you're doing Frank you're doing a
great deal for the holography community
I don't think there's anyone else that
does as much as what you do and I think
this book is uh you're just the right
author for it because uh yeah these are
your people I mean they're just uh it
gives a real good introduction to the
view of Photography I'm sure people will
be very happy with it okay well thank
you very much for taking the time to
come on whole talk thank you very much
and hang on the line I want to talk to
you after I close out here
see you next week everyone remember we
have guests each and every week and next
week we're going to continue our program
with the recordings that we did at the
center for the holographic arts in Long
Island City New York and I hope you tune
in then take care bye